Guide to the José Muñoz Papers MSS.429
Fales Library and Special Collections
José Muñoz Papers
1970s-2014
Fales Library and Special Collections
Muñoz, José Esteban
Pellegrini, Ann, 1964-
Muñoz, Antonio
Muñoz, Elena
MSS.429
6.50 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes, 3 folders in a shared oversize flat box, and born digital physical carriers stored in 2 shared media boxes
20.02 Gigabytes in 1,379 computer files
7 videocassettes (vhs)
1 Cassettes microcassette
3 audiocassettes
8 videocassettes (minidv)
José Muñoz (1967-2013) was a writer, scholar, and professor focused on performance studies, visual culture, queer theory, cultural studies, and critical theory. The José Muñoz Papers contain digital and paper files, and audiovisual material related to Muñoz's life and career as professor and chair of the Department of Performance Studies at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts during the 2000s-2010s. This collection contains NYU course-related files; resumes and biographical sketches; writing drafts and published articles; research/source files and recordings; conference and lecture panel planning material; photographs; college ephemera; and correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 2015 by Antonio and Elena Muñoz, followed by an accretion in October 2016 by NYU professor Ann Pellegrini. The accession numbers associated with this donation are 2015.429 and 2016.050.
Appraisal
The following were removed from the collection: 40 VHS, 6 DVDs, 2 audiocassettes, and 3 CDs (commercial, blank, damaged, or duplicate); 79 phonographic discs; Urkel doll; Keanu Reeves Matrix Action Figure; Polaroid camera; Political Asylum Game; ceramic Cuban flag artwork; 5 movie and exhibition posters; 3 college yearbooks, and 6 cartons of books and magazines. 130 born-digital carriers were also removed from the collection found to be blank, commercial, or damaged.
Arrangement
Organized in two series:
Series I. Professional
Series II. Personal
The files within each series are arranged chronologically, with materials grouped by subject and arranged chronologically within.
Biographical Note
José Esteban Muñoz (1967-2013) was a Cuban American academic in the fields of performance studies, visual culture, queer theory, cultural studies, and critical theory. He received both his undergraduate degree from Sarah Lawrence College (1989) and his doctorate from Duke University (1994) in comparative literature.
Muñoz was a professor and chair of the Department of Performance Studies at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts and wrote extensively on visual art and aesthetics. He was also the editor of the journals Social Text and Women and Performance: A Journal of Feminist Theory.
Muñoz's writing focused on the role of race within gay and lesbian studies as expressed in his first book Disidentifications: Queers of Color and the Performance of Politics (1999). A decade later, his second book Cruising Utopia: The Then and There of Queer Futurity (2009) was published.
Custodial History
The 2016 accretion materials were packed and removed from professor Ann Pellegrini's office.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
The José Muñoz Papers (1970s-2014) contain materials related to the personal life and career of José Esteban Muñoz, a scholar and writer in the field of queer politics and aesthetics, as well as a professor and chair for the Department of Performance Studies at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts. The collection contains digital and paper files documenting performance studies and queer theory as academic disciplines through Muñoz's NYU course material dating from the 2000s to mid-2010s. This collection not only illustrates relevant topics taught at a university during the 2000s, but also the scholarly works produced during this time through his drafts, proofs, and published articles. His writings discuss topics including queer performance artists of color and the role their art plays within their lives and community. Related academic conference and lecture programs and scripts are also in this collection. A large number of personal photographs within this collection, the majority of which are digital, illustrate the life of a young academic and professor living and working in New York. Photographic subjects include travel, friends, his dogs, arts events, parties, and selfies and portraits of Muñoz, taken during the late 1990s-2010s. Ephemera from his studies at Duke University in the 1990s include class papers and assigned readings, as well as event posters and fliers from film and performance events he was involved with as a student.
Performance art -- 20th century; Queer theory.; Identity politics; Art and race; Hispanic Americans -- Ethnic identity; Homosexuality and art; Articles.; Programs (documents); Latino/a/x queer people; Performance art -- United States.; Photographs.; Queer identity; Queer art; Intersectionality; Pellegrini, Ann, 1964-; Muñoz, Antonio; Muñoz, Elena; New York University -- Tisch School of the Arts
- Series I. Professional, 1970s-2013; 3.34 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes; 20 Gigabytes in 432 computer files; 7 videocassettes (vhs); 8 videocassettes (minidv); 1 Cassettes microcassette; 2 audiocassettes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material related to José Muñoz's professional career as a professor and scholarly writer, specifically on queer politics and aesthetics. Muñoz taught college courses during the early to mid-2000s within the Department of Performance Studies at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts. This series contains paper and digital files with course syllabi, course descriptions and announcements, copies of required readings, and departmental correspondence. Muñoz's course material not only represents a sampling of the topics taught at NYU, but also dovetails with themes he wrote about in his essays, articles, books, and presentations. His themes included Latin America and queer sexualities; the overall idea of queerness; and queer artists of color and their positionality in the performance art world. Muñoz also wrote on individual performers and artists including Vaginal Davis, Nao Bustamonte, Bola de Nieve, Andy Warhol, and the band The Gun Club. His writings are documented in this series through drafts, edited proofs, and copies of published articles. This series also contains a selection of Muñoz's source material in paper, digital, and audiovisual formats used to support his scholarly works. Files include exhibition catalogs; event programs; and articles written by others, as well as analog and digital audiovisual recordings of performance art and drag performances. Source material in this series also includes small independent publications from the 1990s, mostly focusing on queer lifestyle and culture. Titles include Pansy Beat, Old, My Comrade, A La Brava, and Perra! Muñoz's involvement as a member of a performance group named Coco Frio during the 2000s includes audio and video performance recordings, scripts, and notes. His engagement with professional conferences and lectures, either as a coordinator and/or speaker is documented in this series through event programs, notes, script drafts, and correspondence.
  - Research/Source Material -- Exhibition Catalogs and Related, 1970s-2004 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Research/Source Material -- Notated Articles and Essays, 1977, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Research/Source Material -- Pansy Beat, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Research/Source Material -- Vaginal Davis, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Research/Source Material -- Vaginal Davis Performance Recordings, circa 1990s, 2010, 2012, Undated (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_29)
  - Research/Source Material -- Old, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Research/Source Material -- Essays by Leti Volpp, 1990s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Research/Source Material -- My Comrade, 1991, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Research/Source Material -- Harness N Hairnet, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Research/Source Material -- A La Brava, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Research/Source Material -- Perra!, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Research/Source Material -- Gab, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Research/Source Material -- Topical Treatments, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Research/Source Material -- Articles and Chapter Sections, 1998-2012 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - Research/Source Material -- Bi Tribune, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Research/Source Material -- Asian Performance Art, 2004-2013 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Research/Source Material, 2004-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_7)
  - Research/Source Material -- Suicide, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Research/Source Material -- The Gun Club, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 12, Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Research/Source Material -- Bola de Nieve, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Research/Source Material -- X (American Band), 2013 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Research/Source Material -- Articles, Papers, Publications, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4-7)
  - Artwork Images, 1973-1997, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Di Prima / Baraka Reading, July 1978 (Box 9, Audiocassette 429.0011)
  - Bubble People, 1983 (Box 9, Vhs 429.0006)
  - Performance Recordings -- Multiple Events, circa 1990s-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_28)
  - Appearances, Lectures, Conferences, 1991-2013 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Appearances, Lectures, Conferences, 2001-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_1)
  - Writings -- "A Phenomenology of Browness: Flesh and Feelings", circa 1990s-2010s (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Writings -- "A Jeté Out the Window: Fred Herko's Incandescent Illumination", circa 1990s-2010s (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Writings -- "Hope in the Face of Heartbreak", circa 1990s-2010s (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Writings -- "The Utopian Impulse in Queer Art and Politics", circa 1990s-2010s (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Writings -- "Latino Rapture: Ethnic Affect and the Politics of Feeling", circa 1990s-2010s (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Writings -- "Tongson Response" and Untitled Works, circa 1990s-2010s (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - Writings -- "Touching Brown, Touching Poverty", circa 1990s-2010s (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Writings -- Pop Out: Queer Warhol Publisher Catalog and Letter, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Writings -- Disidentification Publisher Catalog, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Writings -- "Feeling Brown: Ethnicity and Affect in Ricardo Bracho's The Sweetest Hangover (and Other STDs)", 2000 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Writings -- Essay Review Guidelines and Article for Aztlán: A Journal of Chicano Studies, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Writings -- Script, Creeps with Guinevere Turner, circa 2002 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Writings -- "The Virtuosity of Queer Failure: Living in the Shadow of Jack Smith's Atlantis", circa 2003 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Writings -- A Companion to LGBT/Q Studies Publishing Agreement, Contributor Notes, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Writings -- Papers, Proposals, Essays, Chapters, 2004-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_18)
  - Writings -- Essays and Articles, 2005-2008 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Writings -- Re: Andy Warhol, 2005-2006 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_16)
  - Writings -- I Remember Heaven: Jim Hodges and Andy Warhol Exhibition, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Writings -- The Sense of Watching Tony Sleeping, 2004-2009 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_12)
  - Writings -- Cruising Utopia, Publisher Catalog, Publicity, Drafts, and Event Program, 2004-2013 (Box 5, Folder 6, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_15)
  - Writings -- Cruising the Toilet: LeRoi Jones/Amiri Baraka…, 2005-2006 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_14)
  - Writings -- Author Queries for Article "From surface to depth, between psychoanalysis and affect", 2009 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Writings -- Re: Ana Mendieta, 2010-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_19)
  - Writings -- Gimme Gimme This...Gimme Gimme That…, 2010-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_17)
  - Writings -- Wise Latinas, 2010-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_21)
  - Writings -- Books Containing to Muñoz Work References, 2012 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Writings -- The Brown Commons: The Sense of Wildness, 2012-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_20)
  - Writings -- Amateur: The Work of Nao Bustamonte, 2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_13)
  - Correspondence, 1997-2002 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 2005-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_3)
  - Exhibitions and Events -- Promotional Material and Catalogs, 1997-2013 (Box 5, Folder 17, Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Coco Frio -- Video Recording, May 2001 (Box 9, Minidv 429.0018)
  - Coco Frio -- Audio Recording, May 2001 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_24)
  - Coco Frio -- Notes, 2004, 2006 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_2)
  - Coco Frio -- "Spicville", September 2008 (Box 9, Minidv 429.0016)
  - Coco Frio -- Video Recordings, circa 1990s-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_30)
  - CoCo Frio -- Script, Notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
  - Coco Frio -- Portrait of Wrongness, Undated (Box 9, Minidv 429.0013)
  - Coco Frio -- Footage, Undated (Box 9, Minidv 429.0014)
  - Teaching -- Class Descriptions, Assignments, and Announcements, 1999-2013 (Box 6, Folder 5, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_10)
  - Teaching -- Symphony of Voices Concert/Testimonials Program, for Nomination of Muñoz for Teaching Award, April 2004 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Teaching -- Faculty-Related, 2004-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_11)
  - Teaching -- Introduction to Performance Studies Class Readings, Summer 2007 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Teaching -- Happening/Performance/Event Conference Program, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Teaching -- Faculty Retreat Agenda, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Dynasty Handbag Performance at Dixon Place, New York City, August 2003-August 2004, 2006
    - Video, August 2003-August 2004 (Box 9, Vhs 429.0001)
    - Video, August 2003-August 2004, 2006 (Box 9, Vhs 429.0003)
  - Social Text Project, 2004 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_9)
  - Outfest Platinum Series "F", 2004-2006 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_5)
  - Outfest Platinum Series "F" -- Call for Entries, Description, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Resumes and Biographical Sketches, 2004-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_8)
  - "Cast No Shadow" Performance Promotional Material, Catalog, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "The Gang" Music Recording, June 11, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_23)
  - Notes, 2012-2013, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9-10, Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Filthy Mouth Queer Theory Conference or Psychoanalysis, August 2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_27)
  - New Slaves -- Performance, September 2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_25)
  - Muñoz's Interview with Vaginal Davis, Transcript, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Bra Burning with Levitation" Performance -- Marget Long, Undated (Box 9, Minidv 429.0015)
  - "Lifestyle", Nao Bustamante Performance, Undated (Box 9, Minidv 429.0019)
  - The Weather Underground, Undated (Box 9, Vhs 429.0004)
  - Magnetic Fields "Naveed", Undated (Box 9, Vhs 429.0005)
  - One Year Performance, Undated (Box 9, Vhs 429.0007)
  - Musica Pa' Viejos (For Tio), Undated (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_26)
  - For Professor Muñoz: On and On; Tearz, Undated (Box 9, Audiocassette 429.0012)
  - Carmelita Tropicana Decade Show, Undated (Box 9, Vhs 429.0002)
  - Unknown Event -- Audio Recording, Undated (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_22)
  - Untitled Audio Recording, Undated (Box 9, Cassette 429.0009)
  - Untitled Video Recording, Undated (Box 9, Minidv 429.0008)
  - Texture Footage, Undated (Box 9, Minidv 429.0017)
- Series II. Personal, 1990-2014; 2 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 3 folders in a shared oversize flat box; 551 Megabytes in 947 computer files; 1 audiocassette
  This series contains material from Muñoz's personal life. Ephemera from his doctoral studies at Duke University in the early 1990s include class papers and readings as well as event programs and posters from his involvement in student projects related to performance art and film, including Screen/Society events. Correspondence between friends and family date from the 1990s to mid-2010s. The series contains a significant number of photographs taken by Muñoz and others, often with a phone camera, including selfies and portraits of Muñoz, his two dogs, friends, travel, parties in his home, and arts-related events and performances. These photographs date from 2007 to 2010. This series also contains a program from his memorial service sponsored by NYU in 2014, small artworks potentially created by Muñoz, contact lists, an address book, and ephemera given by friends and family.
  - Duke University -- Class Papers, Readings, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 6-8)
  - Duke University -- Screening Latinidad Project, Event Program, February 1994 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Duke University -- Screen/Society Event Posters and Announcements, 1990-1992 (Box 8, Folder 1, Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1990, 2007-2011, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2004-2013 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_4)
  - Ephemera, Collectibles, and Artworks, 1992-1998, 2002, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3, 6, Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 21)
  - LTTR (Listen Translate Translate Record) Issue #2 with Photograph of Muñoz and Friends, circa 2003 (Box Shared Fales 093, Folder 20)
  - Photographs and Slides -- Events, Parties, Friends, Muñoz Portraits, Dogs, 2007-2010, Undated (Box 8, Folder 4-5, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_429_ER_6)
  - Muñoz Memorial Service Program at NYU, February 2014 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Contact Lists and Address Book, Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Music Mix Tape, Undated (Box 9, Audiocassette 429.0010)